Now, let's chat about views, routes, and templates.
Views and routes allow us to map URLs in our web application to pages, API, and points, and more.
Our blog right now has three different sections.
There's an index here that will show all of our posts.
If I click on Read More, I go to a detail page.
And I also have an about page right here that is at slash about.
So, we have routes that are defined in at the project level in practical blog URLs.py and at the
at level at blogslash URL.py.
Let's take a quick look at those side by side.
So, on the left hand side is the practical blog URL configuration.
This is the top level configuration for everything.
Here, I'm including a path to the admin, which we'll look at in just a second.
It's one of the built-in things about Django that is really fantastic.
The next thing is an include of blog.URLs.
So, that's going to take all of the URLs that I've defined in my app specific blog.URLs and import them here.
So, looking at URLs.py in blog, this is where you'll see I've defined the index,
the about page and the detail page.
And that is the path that I'm passing in as the first argument.
We also have some templates.
And those are located in the blog templates blog directory.
So, a bit of a weird data structure, but that is what Django expects.
We also have static blog CSS.
If I take a look at base.html, this is just the base template that all of my other templates will use.
It's got a header and a footer and all of those reusable elements.
I need to call load static at the top here, which means load up all of the static resources I might need.
Such as my CSS.
These funky looking tags with the curly braces and the percent symbols are template tags.
And those allow you to use some special commands in your HTML templates that let them interface with Django.
Now, the important thing in base.html is this block right here.
This content blocks, let's us know that we can use base.html as a template.
If I then take a look at about.html, I have a template directive here that says,
extend this one from blog base.html.
And then everything that is in between these block content blocks insert that right into here, right into the matching content blocks.
So that is pretty straightforward. We have a post list that has a little bit of a more complex template tag usage.
Here we have a four loop.
We are getting a post list variable passed into this template from our view, which we'll look at in just a second.
And we're looping over it, so for every post that we have we're going to display it.
And then for the detail, we are using a post variable and we're pulling out the post title, the post created at date and the post dot body.
The slug is being used here for the read more button.
We're passing in, we're using this URL template tag and we're passing in post, which is the name of the view.
Followed by the slug.
This matches our URL defined here in URLs.py.
So that lets us get a link to the detail view.
Now, we're going to take a quick look at views.
These are some simple basic views that you might define when you're first starting out.
But the more advanced concept is class-based views.
So here we have our defined views.
And these views map to the URLs that we have defined in your blog URLs.py.
So here we see views.about views.index views.post.
And we've also given these names so that we can access them from our templates.
Now, this view, the about view, is just getting a template and rendering it and returning an HTTP response.
This index view is taking a post, getting all of the objects in the database via query, creating a context.
So we remember in our template earlier, we used a variable called post underscore list.
This is where it came from, we're passing in here, and then for a detail view in our post.
We're using a shortcut called get object or 404, which means that if a post with the passed in slot isn't found, Django will return a 404 status code.
Now, this is a pattern that you will see over and over in Django.
And so Django has built in some handy shortcuts called class-based views that allow you to take out a lot of this stuff that you might do over and over again.
So I'm going to check out the class-based views branch in the repository.
And we're going to take a look at what class-based views look like.
This is it.
So from Django.views.generic, I have imported detail view, which means give me one object, and I've imported list view, which gets a list of objects.
And I've also imported the model that we care about in this case.
It's post.
So I'm creating a class-based view called post list view that inherits from list view, and I'm telling it what model to use.
If we take a look at our URLs again, they look a little bit different.
Now, you notice that I didn't have the about page in here.
That's because I'm using a class-based view called detail view, our template view, and I'm using it right in URLs.
So I'm calling a method on it called as view, and I'm telling it what template name I care about.
Super quick shortcut.
I'm also calling as view on my imported post list view and post detail view and giving it a name.
Now, this code does the same exact thing that the other code was doing with a lot less craft.
So let me make sure that my server is still running and take a look here, and here we are.
Everything still works as expected.